<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>covid-19 data analysis | KHstats</title>
    <link>/tags/covid-19-data-analysis/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/covid-19-data-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>covid-19 data analysis</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>covid-19 data analysis</title>
      <link>/tags/covid-19-data-analysis/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Sidelines: NYC&#39;s Covid-19 outbreak from the eyes of a biostatistician</title>
      <link>/blog/covid/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/covid/covid/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;link href=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/pagedtable/css/pagedtable.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/pagedtable/js/pagedtable.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is December 2018, and the Pulmonary and Critical Care research team at my hospital in New York City (NYC) needs a new biostatistician. As an eager recent hire in the Biostatistics Department, I fit the bill. I start learning organ failure scoring systems, signs of septic shock, and the various types of mechanical ventilation. My close friend does cutting-edge cancer research, and I feel a bit resentful. Nobody ever wants to hear the controversial definitions of acute respiratory distress syndrome at family parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year and three months later, the coronavirus 2019 (Covid-19) respiratory pandemic hits NYC. Restaurants are instructed to close the day before Saint Patrick’s Day, my birthday. I can’t see friends anymore, so I run to Central Park and sit on the top of the tallest, coldest rock. As the sun disappears behind skyscrapers, my mom texts me that she hopes I had a good day. It would normally be strange for her to nearly miss my birthday, but she is working long hours this week. She is a nursing director back in Michigan, and her hospital is preparing for the impending outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my route home there is a health department sign asking for former healthcare worker volunteers. Before I began my career in biostatistics, I was a nurse technician, so I sign up without hesitation. My misguided logic is that the exploding numbers of Covid-19 will make my critical care collaborators too busy to pursue their research, and this seems like the best way to help as the world descends into chaos. I look up YouTube videos to refresh myself on drawing blood and inserting intravenous lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How absolutely crazy that I thought my biostatistics training wouldn’t be useful, in retrospect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within days, I am told to drop all of my other research projects for Covid-19 work. Our informatics team is using the structure of the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) database I work with as part of a tracking repository for our entire hospital. “Do we have a data dictionary for the ICU database, Kat?” We do have a data dictionary, but the translations of critical care jargon live undocumented inside my brain. I begin working through issues linking SQL tables, aggregating “cytokine storm” labs, and explaining dozens of variables to other analysts at the hospital. Each morning I pull new data and watch the files grow exponentially larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Countless questions are flooding in from every specialty in medicine. The first few weeks, most of them revolve around “who will get intubated, and when?” My hospital, like so many others in NYC, is on track to run out of ventilators soon. My attendance becomes mandatory at multiple “risk prediction” meetings each week. I find myself in charge of extensive data cleaning and then coding models to answer vague and terrifying questions: we need to figure out which patients will “crash,” who can be transferred, and, if we run out of ventilators, who has the best chance to survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a junior researcher, previously unconcerned with hospital operations, suddenly asked to provide rapid answers for potentially immediate decision making. I accept my new role with the utmost seriousness. My days, normally spent coding with double monitors at a proper desk, suddenly fill with Zoom meetings from 8:30-5:00 from a laptop at my kitchen table. Each night after the meetings end, I take advantage of the relative quiet to code into the early hours of the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For several weeks I use the long, uninterrupted hours of weekends to work, waking up with the sun and continuing on until at least 11pm, with few breaks in between. Some nights I send my mom “good morning” texts at 5am. “Did you wake up early or have you not slept yet?” is always her first question. The next is, “No fever? No cough?” She is worried about me, living in the international epicenter, but I am just as worried about her, working at a hospital every day. She informs me that my dad is sleeping in my old bedroom in case she brings the virus home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My best friend and her sister are nurses at the same hospital as my mom. I FaceTime her to check in. Both of their units are now “hot floors;” every room is filled with a Covid-19 patient. They were living with their parents, sister, and cousins but moved to an AirBnb for the foreseeable future. “It’s so crazy here, Kitty,” she tells me in a defeated voice.
Her fellow nurse has been hospitalized with Covid-19 and is on 6L of oxygen. I can’t help but think about the prediction models I’ve been working on. I mentally run his characteristics through them. I know what my models would estimate his probability of intubation to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listen to her talk about the N-95 masks they’ve been given. “Remember how they used to say those were one-time use?” she asks me. I do. “They started telling us they were good for the whole day, and then they said they’d be good for the whole week, and now they’re saying we might have to start sharing.” I wonder what data analyst, perhaps just like me, is crunching those numbers and feeding information to hospital administration. “This virus is so terrible. I’ve never done so much post-mortem care, zipped so many body bags…” Her voice drifts off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel guilty, on the sidelines. I see the raccoon eyes – the only part of their faces visible between hair caps and procedure masks – of the physicians I spend all day hopping on and off meetings with, and I desperately want to help. I cannot hold the hand of a Covid-19 patient but all of their data is at my keystrokes: millions of lab results, vital signs, and procedure codes. I see their inflammatory cytokines spike, I watch their oxygen levels plummet, I can tell you which organs are failing, who’s on which experimental drug, and who’s just been made Do Not Intubate and Do Not Resuscitate. I follow in horror, almost in real-time, the time-stamps of admission, intubation, death. I cannot compare this experience to physically caring for Covid-19 patients, but I feel haunted by it all the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hole up in my tiny studio in Manhattan for days at a time, listening to wails of ambulances and pings of messages from my computer. I see only one friend with frequency; we both live alone, 18 blocks from each other. She texts me often, asking to meet in Central Park. She suspects I am not doing well, and she is right. I walk with her all over the Upper East Side a few times a week, each of us donned in our black cotton masks. We try not to talk about Covid-19, but it’s hard to avoid when our walks take us past the pop-up ICU tents and refrigerated trucks that stretch entire blocks – the overflow morgues for NYC’s dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We try to time our walks so that we’re outside at 7pm, when the city unites to cheer for healthcare workers. If I’m not out walking with her, I climb religiously onto my fire escape to clap. Sometimes a man in the apartment across the street sings Sinatra. &lt;em&gt;I want to wake up in the city that never sleeps… New York, New York!&lt;/em&gt; I’ve only lived here two years, but I miss “the city that never sleeps” so badly it hurts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life continues in this way for me, with no real sense of time or distinguishing events, from mid March until Mother’s Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 10th at 11pm, my cell phone goes off. It is an ominous vibration against my kitchen table, where I am perpetually sitting with my laptop whirring. “Hi Honey… I just wanted to let you know that, mmm…” it’s my mom, and her voice is cracking. I finish the sentence for her, “Aunt Peggy died?” I ask, sadly. “Yes.” “Okay. Thanks for letting me know.” I stare into the white brick wall in front of my kitchen table for so long that I start seeing multicolored spots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My grandfather’s eldest sister, my Aunt Peggy, began showing telltale symptoms of Covid-19 and tested positive only a few days previously. She’d been without any visitors in her assisted living home for months. I think about her red lipstick, elaborately looping handwriting, and her soft voice last Christmas. “How’s New York, Katherine? I’m so proud of you.” She was the first nurse in my family, and she influenced my mom to become a nurse, who influenced me to pursue medical research. Our matriarch left us on Mother’s Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend that night trying to find a rental car company that will allow me to drive one-way to Michigan, but I am several weeks too late in my exodus from NYC. I book a flight instead and leave a few days later on a near-empty plane. I plan to stay with family for two weeks, but I don’t leave for two months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time I write this, it is September. The NYC outbreak has passed, but my Covid-19 research is unceasing. Everyone at the hospital is wary. I attend a meeting with our informatics team. “It’s good to ‘see’ everyone again,” someone says. It’s only half accurate – the circumstances that bring us to meetings together are never good. We discuss data repositories for a possible second wave of Covid-19 as NYC schools and indoor dining reopen. After the call, I feel an immeasurable sadness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I truly don’t know if I can handle another round of it all. Can you?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
