<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>career | KHstats</title>
    <link>/tags/career/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>career</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2019 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>career</title>
      <link>/tags/career/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stats on Drugs: An interview with a Pharmaceutical CRO Biostatistician</title>
      <link>/blog/ditl-cro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/ditl-cro/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/kim1.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I wrote my first blog post, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.khstats.com/blog/ditl-biostats/&#34;&gt;“A Day in the Life of a Biostatistician”&lt;/a&gt;, documenting the granular details of my work as an early career academic research biostatistician. I’m excited to announce I am turning that post into a “day in the life” series in which I interview other biostatisticians with differing roles. My hope is that it will enlighten anyone interested in the field of biostatistics, and especially help undergraduate and current biostatistics Masters students make informed decisions about their careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first interviewee is Kim Hirschhorn, a former classmate and good friend from my time at the University of Michigan School of Public Health. Kim is an avid reality TV show watcher, loves Eggo waffles and Hostess Ho-Hos, and is a great statistician; so great, professors were often confused as to why she wasn’t planning to pursue a PhD. Kim, however, has always been adamant that she doesn’t need a PhD to have the career she wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim’s determination to find a job which allowed for ample career growth with “only” an MS in Biostatistics paid off. After graduating in 2018, she chose to work as a biostatistician at PRA Health Sciences, a Contract Research Organization (CRO) for pharmaceutical companies. Biostatistician roles at CROs offer excellent career trajectory for Masters-level statisticians and don’t have a job title ceiling as some careers in statistics notoriously do for those without a PhD. Additionally, it’s a lucrative job option for a Masters-level biostatistician. (🤑!) For more information on salaries of early career statisticians you can check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://magazine.amstat.org/blog/2019/08/01/mastergraduate/&#34;&gt;American Statistical Association’s recent survey of 2018 Masters in Statistics graduates&lt;/a&gt;. But, to learn more about what Kim actually does as a biostatistician at a pharmaceutical CRO, read on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kat: Thanks for taking the time to chat, Kim! Can you tell me where you work and what the mission of your company is?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kim: I work at the Chicago office of a large CRO called PRA Health Sciences. PRA stands for Pharmaceutical Research Associates, and our primary responsibility is to run clinical trials for pharmaceutical companies. This includes everything from planning the study at an administrative level – such as identifying physicians to recruit patients and administer drug therapies – to collecting data like patients’ disease progression and adverse events, analyzing and summarizing the results, and submitting requests for the successful trials to be approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA). After a pharmaceutical company has researched and developed a potential new drug, we partner with them to implement the various phases of clinical trials necessary to test that drug.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whoa, sometimes I forget about all the steps in a clinical trial. Before we go any further, can you give us a quick explanation about what those phases of clinical trials mean?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are three main phases: Phase I, II, and III. In general, Phase I clinical trials check whether a drug is safe to administer. Sometimes this also involves testing which dosage of a drug is safe – or at least not overwhelmingly toxic – to the body. Phase I trials are usually done on a small group of patients. Phase II trials are done on a larger group of patients and focus on whether the drug is effective, or in other words, whether it can actually fix whatever health problem the pharmaceutical company had in mind when developing it. Most drugs fail in Phase II.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If a drug does move onto a Phase III trial, its performance in comparison to the current standard of care (which is often another drug on the market) is evaluated. In both Phase II and III, patients are randomized into treatment and control groups and typically neither physicians nor patients know which treatment is administered. Even patients who are not receiving a treatment will receive a sugar pill, or placebo drug. Oftentimes a clinical trial’s aims will fall somewhere between two phases, for example, I’ve worked on Phase 1b/2a trials that collect information on safety, determine the recommended dose, and then evaluate the drug’s efficacy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I see, so which of those phases do you work on?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have been a Biostatistician I for a bit over a year now, so that means I am the lead biostatistician on a few simple Phase I trials. There is usually not much statistical testing occurring here; it’s all about how many patients have an adverse response to the drug. Since I am still in the most junior biostatistician role, a lot of my time is spent doing biostatistical support for Phase II and III trials, where more senior biostatisticians oversee my work and pre-specify the analyses. The longer I stay at my job, the more responsibilities I will have and the more complex studies I will lead.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s involved in leading a study, even a “small and simple” phase I? How is that different from the work you do as “biostatistical support” on the Phase II and III trials?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When I am the lead of a study, I am meeting with members of the pharmaceutical company and working with them to develop a statistical analysis plan. Once the clinical trial starts and I begin to receive data, I work with programmers to ensure everything that needs to be done for the analysis is completed in the time allotted by that trial’s budget. Since the studies I am leading now are early phase, I am in charge of doing all the statistical analyses and reporting the results back to the pharmaceutical company. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In contrast, when I am biostatistical support, I am mostly executing analyses already specified in a statistical analysis plan. This typically involves writing macros in the statistical programming language &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sas.com/en_us/software/stat.html&#34;&gt;SAS&lt;/a&gt; to ultimately produce what is dozens of outputs. A large portion of my time as a junior biostatistician is spent figuring out the best way to present that huge amount of data and results in a comprehensible way. Even before I have data from a clinical trial, I have to plan out detailed tables and prepare a shell document for when the data is ready for analysis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who are you working with in your day-to-day roles?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I get assignments from my manager, and then work with the lead biostatisticians on each trial. It is standard in the pharmaceutical industry that all analyses must be independently reproduced. This usually means the lead biostatistician is redoing my analysis without looking at my code, so sometimes I have to work closely with him or her to figure out why our results are not matching. Besides that, I frequently collaborate with the data programmers and statistical programmers in charge of the data for the trials I am working on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data programmers are in charge of taking raw data from the trials, checking it for inconsistencies, and putting it into a standardized form for statistical programmers. Statistical programmers then take those standardized data sets, derive many new variables from those initially collected for each patient, and produce hundreds of tables and figures summarizing the data. In some cases they also help prepare the data for my analyses, for example, they might write code to calculate the number of days or months until each patient experienced disease progression so that I can use that information for statistical models.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If there is a problem with the data when I am running a model, I ask the statistical programmer to check his or her code, and if there is no issue there, the data programmer looks at their code. If necessary, the data programmer may go back to the clinical sites who are collecting the data from patients and ask them to correct any missing information or inconsistencies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sounds like your data is in pretty good shape when it arrives to you, then!
Earlier you mentioned writing macros in SAS. Does everyone use SAS? Could you use R or another programming language if you wanted?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have used R for a few side analyses, such as a data mining analysis. However, the industry standard for pharmaceuticals has always been SAS. I don’t foresee that changing anytime soon. Although a huge benefit of R is that it is free and open source software, meaning anyone can contribute code in a package, SAS has the advantage that if you run a certain type of statistical model, you can be absolutely sure that is what ran on your data. Because SAS is a paid software, it is liable for what it says it is doing, and there is always support on hand if you have questions about errors or results you are getting from any given data procedure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your hours like? What sort of flexibility do you have for vacation, or working remotely?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I usually get in at 8:15 and leave somewhere between 4:45 and 5:15. I do get a lot of vacation days, with the caveat that if there is a deliverable deadline for a project I’m working on, I may not be able to take my vacation during that time. As for working remotely, it’s an option I have as-needed, such as if I have a doctor’s appointment. The job can definitely be done 100% remotely, and in fact many members of the company work remotely, but it’s not really an option for a Biostatistician I to do all the time because we rely so heavily on our senior biostatisticians. I prefer that, though - it’s easier for me to work in the office!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How will your roles and responsibilities change as you progress as a biostatistician at a CRO?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When I said a lot of my time is spent working on table shells and report planning, I think it’s worth acknowledging that that is not a very exciting activity. However, as a Biostatistician I progresses to Biostatistician II, Senior Biostatistician, Principal Biostatistician, Senior Principal Biostatistician, etc., a lot of those more mundane (in my opinion) tasks decrease. You are in charge of much more complex studies and specifying the statistical analyses for that clinical trial. The work also naturally becomes more managerial.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being in charge of a trial means meeting with both external clients and internal company leadership, setting timelines for data/statistical programmers and junior biostatisticians, answering questions that come up about data and analyses, maintaining oversight of the hours each team member is spending on the project, and tracking the corresponding budget carefully. As biostatisticians progress in the career ladder at a CRO, they have some flexibility in how much data they actually analyze on a day-to-day basis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What made you decide to take this position at a CRO over your other offers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well of course it’s not all about money, but this was one of the highest offers I received, so that helped. The potential for career growth was also very appealing to me. Typically after about 4-5 years you are a Senior Biostatistician and qualified to lead any study. But, you can lead studies long before this if the pharmaceutical company agrees you are qualified to do so. I really like that career progression at a pharmaceutical CRO is very much about experience and skills, as opposed to whether or not you hold a PhD. This is often not the case if you work directly for a pharmaceutical company.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, what made you choose to enter the field of Biostatistics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have always been drawn to a career in public health. During my first year at the University of Illinois, I was a stereotypical freshman pre-med student. I ultimately changed my mind about medical school and got a Bachelor’s degree in statistics, but I still took several epidemiology and biology classes just because I found them interesting. Math has always been my strongest subject, but I wanted to find a way to combine it with my other interests. After doing a fair share of Googling, I found the field of Biostatistics. I met with the head of U of I’s Statistics MS program, and he shared his experience of working in industry as a biostatistician before becoming a professor. He spoke very highly of the field and gave me a lot of great information on the types of careers I could have with a Masters in Statistics or Biostatistics. I was pretty much sold after that meeting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking back, are you happy with your decision to do a Masters in Biostatistics, rather than Statistics or Applied Statistics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, I’m really happy I decided on a Masters in Biostatistics. Throughout my program, our applied problem sets were always related to medicine or healthcare in some way, and it was easy for me to take health-specific statistics classes, such as a clinical trials methodology course. Since I was pretty sure I wanted to go into healthcare, I think biostatistics was a great decision for me, because a Masters in Biostatistics shows my passion for the field and may give me an edge over similar applicants who have a more general Masters in Statistics or Applied Statistics. I still find public health to be the most interesting sector to practice statistics in, so I think the degree will always be to my advantage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks so much for chatting, Kim!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have other questions for Kim, or if there are careers within biostatistics you’d like to hear about, feel free to email me and let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kat&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stats on Drugs: An interview with a Pharmaceutical CRO Biostatistician</title>
      <link>/blog/ditl_kim/ditl_kim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/ditl_kim/ditl_kim/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/kim1.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I wrote my first blog post, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.khstats.com/blog/ditl-biostats/&#34;&gt;“A Day in the Life of a Biostatistician”&lt;/a&gt;, documenting the granular details of my work as an early career academic research biostatistician. I’m excited to announce I am turning that post into a “day in the life” series in which I interview other biostatisticians with differing roles. My hope is that it will enlighten anyone interested in the field of biostatistics, and especially help undergraduate and current biostatistics Masters students make informed decisions about their careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first interviewee is Kim Hirschhorn, a former classmate and good friend from my time at the University of Michigan School of Public Health. Kim is an avid reality TV show watcher, loves Eggo waffles and Hostess Ho-Hos, and is a great statistician; so great, professors were often confused as to why she wasn’t planning to pursue a PhD. Kim, however, has always been adamant that she doesn’t need a PhD to have the career she wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim’s determination to find a job which allowed for ample career growth with “only” an MS in Biostatistics paid off. After graduating in 2018, she chose to work as a biostatistician at PRA Health Sciences, a Contract Research Organization (CRO) for pharmaceutical companies. Biostatistician roles at CROs offer excellent career trajectory for Masters-level statisticians and don’t have a job title ceiling as some careers in statistics notoriously do for those without a PhD. Additionally, it’s a lucrative job option for a Masters-level biostatistician. (🤑!) For more information on salaries of early career statisticians you can check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://magazine.amstat.org/blog/2019/08/01/mastergraduate/&#34;&gt;American Statistical Association’s recent survey of 2018 Masters in Statistics graduates&lt;/a&gt;. But, to learn more about what Kim actually does as a biostatistician at a pharmaceutical CRO, read on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kat: Thanks for taking the time to chat, Kim! Can you tell me where you work and what the mission of your company is?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kim: I work at the Chicago office of a large CRO called PRA Health Sciences. PRA stands for Pharmaceutical Research Associates, and our primary responsibility is to run clinical trials for pharmaceutical companies. This includes everything from planning the study at an administrative level – such as identifying physicians to recruit patients and administer drug therapies – to collecting data like patients’ disease progression and adverse events, analyzing and summarizing the results, and submitting requests for the successful trials to be approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA). After a pharmaceutical company has researched and developed a potential new drug, we partner with them to implement the various phases of clinical trials necessary to test that drug.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whoa, sometimes I forget about all the steps in a clinical trial. Before we go any further, can you give us a quick explanation about what those phases of clinical trials mean?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are three main phases: Phase I, II, and III. In general, Phase I clinical trials check whether a drug is safe to administer. Sometimes this also involves testing which dosage of a drug is safe – or at least not overwhelmingly toxic – to the body. Phase I trials are usually done on a small group of patients. Phase II trials are done on a larger group of patients and focus on whether the drug is effective, or in other words, whether it can actually fix whatever health problem the pharmaceutical company had in mind when developing it. Most drugs fail in Phase II.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If a drug does move onto a Phase III trial, its performance in comparison to the current standard of care (which is often another drug on the market) is evaluated. In both Phase II and III, patients are randomized into treatment and control groups and typically neither physicians nor patients know which treatment is administered. Even patients who are not receiving a treatment will receive a sugar pill, or placebo drug. Oftentimes a clinical trial’s aims will fall somewhere between two phases, for example, I’ve worked on Phase 1b/2a trials that collect information on safety, determine the recommended dose, and then evaluate the drug’s efficacy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I see, so which of those phases do you work on?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have been a Biostatistician I for a bit over a year now, so that means I am the lead biostatistician on a few simple Phase I trials. There is usually not much statistical testing occurring here; it’s all about how many patients have an adverse response to the drug. Since I am still in the most junior biostatistician role, a lot of my time is spent doing biostatistical support for Phase II and III trials, where more senior biostatisticians oversee my work and pre-specify the analyses. The longer I stay at my job, the more responsibilities I will have and the more complex studies I will lead.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s involved in leading a study, even a “small and simple” phase I? How is that different from the work you do as “biostatistical support” on the Phase II and III trials?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When I am the lead of a study, I am meeting with members of the pharmaceutical company and working with them to develop a statistical analysis plan. Once the clinical trial starts and I begin to receive data, I work with programmers to ensure everything that needs to be done for the analysis is completed in the time allotted by that trial’s budget. Since the studies I am leading now are early phase, I am in charge of doing all the statistical analyses and reporting the results back to the pharmaceutical company. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In contrast, when I am biostatistical support, I am mostly executing analyses already specified in a statistical analysis plan. This typically involves writing macros in the statistical programming language &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sas.com/en_us/software/stat.html&#34;&gt;SAS&lt;/a&gt; to ultimately produce what is dozens of outputs. A large portion of my time as a junior biostatistician is spent figuring out the best way to present that huge amount of data and results in a comprehensible way. Even before I have data from a clinical trial, I have to plan out detailed tables and prepare a shell document for when the data is ready for analysis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who are you working with in your day-to-day roles?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I get assignments from my manager, and then work with the lead biostatisticians on each trial. It is standard in the pharmaceutical industry that all analyses must be independently reproduced. This usually means the lead biostatistician is redoing my analysis without looking at my code, so sometimes I have to work closely with him or her to figure out why our results are not matching. Besides that, I frequently collaborate with the data programmers and statistical programmers in charge of the data for the trials I am working on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data programmers are in charge of taking raw data from the trials, checking it for inconsistencies, and putting it into a standardized form for statistical programmers. Statistical programmers then take those standardized data sets, derive many new variables from those initially collected for each patient, and produce hundreds of tables and figures summarizing the data. In some cases they also help prepare the data for my analyses, for example, they might write code to calculate the number of days or months until each patient experienced disease progression so that I can use that information for statistical models.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If there is a problem with the data when I am running a model, I ask the statistical programmer to check his or her code, and if there is no issue there, the data programmer looks at their code. If necessary, the data programmer may go back to the clinical sites who are collecting the data from patients and ask them to correct any missing information or inconsistencies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sounds like your data is in pretty good shape when it arrives to you, then!
Earlier you mentioned writing macros in SAS. Does everyone use SAS? Could you use R or another programming language if you wanted?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have used R for a few side analyses, such as a data mining analysis. However, the industry standard for pharmaceuticals has always been SAS. I don’t foresee that changing anytime soon. Although a huge benefit of R is that it is free and open source software, meaning anyone can contribute code in a package, SAS has the advantage that if you run a certain type of statistical model, you can be absolutely sure that is what ran on your data. Because SAS is a paid software, it is liable for what it says it is doing, and there is always support on hand if you have questions about errors or results you are getting from any given data procedure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your hours like? What sort of flexibility do you have for vacation, or working remotely?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I usually get in at 8:15 and leave somewhere between 4:45 and 5:15. I do get a lot of vacation days, with the caveat that if there is a deliverable deadline for a project I’m working on, I may not be able to take my vacation during that time. As for working remotely, it’s an option I have as-needed, such as if I have a doctor’s appointment. The job can definitely be done 100% remotely, and in fact many members of the company work remotely, but it’s not really an option for a Biostatistician I to do all the time because we rely so heavily on our senior biostatisticians. I prefer that, though - it’s easier for me to work in the office!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How will your roles and responsibilities change as you progress as a biostatistician at a CRO?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When I said a lot of my time is spent working on table shells and report planning, I think it’s worth acknowledging that that is not a very exciting activity. However, as a Biostatistician I progresses to Biostatistician II, Senior Biostatistician, Principal Biostatistician, Senior Principal Biostatistician, etc., a lot of those more mundane (in my opinion) tasks decrease. You are in charge of much more complex studies and specifying the statistical analyses for that clinical trial. The work also naturally becomes more managerial.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being in charge of a trial means meeting with both external clients and internal company leadership, setting timelines for data/statistical programmers and junior biostatisticians, answering questions that come up about data and analyses, maintaining oversight of the hours each team member is spending on the project, and tracking the corresponding budget carefully. As biostatisticians progress in the career ladder at a CRO, they have some flexibility in how much data they actually analyze on a day-to-day basis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What made you decide to take this position at a CRO over your other offers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well of course it’s not all about money, but this was one of the highest offers I received, so that helped. The potential for career growth was also very appealing to me. Typically after about 4-5 years you are a Senior Biostatistician and qualified to lead any study. But, you can lead studies long before this if the pharmaceutical company agrees you are qualified to do so. I really like that career progression at a pharmaceutical CRO is very much about experience and skills, as opposed to whether or not you hold a PhD. This is often not the case if you work directly for a pharmaceutical company.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, what made you choose to enter the field of Biostatistics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have always been drawn to a career in public health. During my first year at the University of Illinois, I was a stereotypical freshman pre-med student. I ultimately changed my mind about medical school and got a Bachelor’s degree in statistics, but I still took several epidemiology and biology classes just because I found them interesting. Math has always been my strongest subject, but I wanted to find a way to combine it with my other interests. After doing a fair share of Googling, I found the field of Biostatistics. I met with the head of U of I’s Statistics MS program, and he shared his experience of working in industry as a biostatistician before becoming a professor. He spoke very highly of the field and gave me a lot of great information on the types of careers I could have with a Masters in Statistics or Biostatistics. I was pretty much sold after that meeting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking back, are you happy with your decision to do a Masters in Biostatistics, rather than Statistics or Applied Statistics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, I’m really happy I decided on a Masters in Biostatistics. Throughout my program, our applied problem sets were always related to medicine or healthcare in some way, and it was easy for me to take health-specific statistics classes, such as a clinical trials methodology course. Since I was pretty sure I wanted to go into healthcare, I think biostatistics was a great decision for me, because a Masters in Biostatistics shows my passion for the field and may give me an edge over similar applicants who have a more general Masters in Statistics or Applied Statistics. I still find public health to be the most interesting sector to practice statistics in, so I think the degree will always be to my advantage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks so much for chatting, Kim!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have other questions for Kim, or if there are careers within biostatistics you’d like to hear about, feel free to email me and let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kat&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Day in the Life of a Biostatistician</title>
      <link>/blog/ditl-biostats/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/ditl-biostats/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;It seems fitting that my first blog post is on a topic that I tried and failed to find via Google search a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll back up for a second. A few years ago I was a recent college graduate, and trying hard to “figure out my life.” My major was biochemistry, which is one of those degrees where 99%* of people just keep on going to school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was working full-time night-shift at a hospital as a patient care technician. The key word in that sentence is “night-shift” which meant that even on my days off, I didn’t sleep at night, but all my friends and family did. So, I was often alone and awake, with a lot of time to think about my future… and surf the web for potential careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/sadcat.png&#34; width=&#34;340px&#34; height=&#34;450px&#34; alt=&#34;cat&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew I wanted a job in healthcare, but I was confused as to where in medicine would be a good fit for me. I could visualize very clearly what my days at work would look like if I were to become a physician, or a physician assistant, or a registered nurse (all careers I developed lengthy pros and cons lists for).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there was another career involving medicine that I was drawn to but didn’t know enough about. “Biostatistics” was a class biochemistry majors took at my university, but I had been exempted because I took AP Statistics in high school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, biostatistics seemed to be the application of some high school-level math to biological problems. I had no concept of what a degree in biostatistics, and much less a career as a biostatistician, could entail. Endless Google searches with some variant of “what does a biostatistician do” and even “day in the life of a biostatistician” had not given me a very good picture of what I would actually be doing as a biostatistician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ultimately lucked out during a conversation with a professor during my senior year of college. I was rambling about my many life plans and he mentioned his cousin was the chair of a well-known Biostatistics program. He encouraged me to email her my questions about biostatistics, and I am so grateful she took time to respond with detailed answers. Her description of life as a biostatistician was enough for me to choose going to graduate school for an MS in biostatistics over medical school/physician assistant school/second-degree nursing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel wholeheartedly that although I would have enjoyed my life as an MD/PA/RN, biostatistics is the right career for me. So, in honor of my confused younger self, and as a way of paying it forward, I’ve dedicated this topic for my very first blog post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/maz.png&#34; alt=&#34;ma&#34;width=&#34;400px&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full disclaimer - what follows is a day in the life of one masters-level, academic research-focused biostatistician and I cannot make claims about the careers of statisticians in industry or pharmaceuticals or hospitals or government. In addition, here’s a bit more background before I get into the granular details of my work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My official job description is to assist investigators (i.e. physicians or PhD-level researchers with a scientific question) throughout all stages of the scientific research process. This means helping with study design, data collection, data cleaning (also known as getting the data in the right form for analysis and making sure nothing is obviously incorrect), data visualization, statistical analysis, reporting and explaining my results, and writing methods and results sections for scientific papers. You will soon see that on any given day I am working on multiple projects at various stages of this process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will mention R/Rstudio a bit. For those who are not familiar with it, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source (which means anyone can help contribute) programming language that is well-equipped for statistical analysis. It’s arguably very similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.python.org/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, which is a more widely used language, but statisticians tend to use R more because its statistical packages are very well-developed. During grad school I used Python because I worked in a computational biology lab, and I learned &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sas.com/en_us/home.html&#34;&gt;SAS&lt;/a&gt; (another statistical programming language) in some of my classes, but R is what I prefer these days. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;Rstudio&lt;/a&gt; is a platform that makes it more user friendly to use R.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, without further ado! An average day**:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/desk.png&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34; height=&#34;375px&#34; alt=&#34;desky&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9:30AM - I arrive at my office and spend a few minutes chatting with my coworkers. To set the scene for you, I have a fairly spacious cubicle within a group of five other cubicles. I sit next to another research biostatistician, two health informatics professionals, and two clinical trial grant specialists. I’m actually not completely sure what that last pair’s title is, but I know their primary task is to make sure several multi-million dollar clinical trial grants stay funded (woah). Everyone I sit by is young and goofy, but very driven, making for a fun office environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9:45AM - I check and answer new emails from researchers I collaborate on projects with. I send my availability for a meeting to a group of doctors who want to go over the results of a recent analysis I did on Body Mass Index and death rates in the Intensive Care Unit. In a different thread of emails, I thank several researchers from another university for clarifying their methods and sending me code for an analysis similar to one I will soon work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:00AM - I open a manuscript draft for a paper I received yesterday. It’s from a group of residents and medical students I worked with a few months ago. Their study looks at the association between blood levels of a certain biomarker and the time to death in cancer patients. My role in the analysis was to examine the associations between several biomarkers such as phosphorus, phosphate, and calcitriol. I then fit a regression model, just like y=mx+b, but with way more math. For this analysis I used a model for when your y is a time to an event (death, in this case), fittingly called a survival model. After adjusting for confounding factors like age, which affects both tumor progression and biomarker levels, there was a significant association between the biomarker and time to death in cancer patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers have asked for my assistance in writing the methods section. The methods section of a scientific article is the steps the scientists took to analyze data explicitly written out for anyone looking to review or learn about their work. I read through their current draft of the paper carefully, make some edits, and send it back. They are hoping to submit this paper to a peer-reviewed journal within a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/KM.png&#34; width=&#34;650px&#34; height=&#34;500px&#34; alt=&#34;kmplot&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:45AM - I have a weekly meeting a few blocks from my office with a neurologist I spend a large portion of my time working with. She is a leader in the field of Alzheimer’s research, and I find it very rewarding to work on her data and be a small part of a growing body of research in the field. I am “contracted” out to her research as I am to all of the researchers I work with—it’s how my institution budgets funding for grants. One of the faculty-level biostatisticians in my department—which means he has a PhD and specializes in certain statistical methods—is also part of this contract, and some days, like today, he joins me at these meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11:00AM - This week’s meeting is pretty straightforward. We discuss how we can improve one of the neurologist’s National Institute of Health grants from a statistics standpoint. The statistical methods for this project can get complicated, in part because we are looking at the brain scans of women in different stages of menopause over time, and we have to consider age as a confounding factor. We want to convey to the reviewers of our grant how we plan to do this. Since this is a methods-focused meeting, I mostly listen and take notes along with two neurology research coordinators that also attend these weekly meetings. When the meeting concludes I have for less work than usual - I only need to make a few graphs representing our study design and past results for inclusion to the grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12:00PM - I head to lunch with a group of coworkers. They have gotten food from a nearby salad place, and we sit in one of our favorite buildings on campus and eat together. Our jokes oscillate from incredibly nerdy to pretty stupid. One of my coworkers points out that our hair is styled the same way for the third day in a row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/katalan.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12:45PM - I get back to my desk and type up my handwritten notes from the neurology meeting and put them in that project’s “Notes” folder. It’s important to me that I keep track of all my meetings electronically - I fear losing my notebooks or someone else having to decipher my cursive should I ever have to pass off a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1:00PM - I start to make a plan for a different analysis I’m working on. This project is something new for me - it involves a protein assay and data for 1000+ different protein expression levels. The researcher I’m working with wants to know which proteins are over- and under-expressed in people with a specific autoimmune disorder and a certain type of lung disease. I’ve recently spoken to some bioinformaticians and have a clearer idea of the analysis I need to do. I draw out a little map of the code organization I think would be the most efficient for this analysis and open up Rstudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/notes.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400px&#34; height=&#34;350px&#34; alt=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1:30PM - I get to work writing up functions, which is just a fancy programming way of saying your code can do the same thing to multiple data sets (or subsets of patients, as is the case of this protein expression study I’m doing). Sometimes it takes a bit longer to write my functions than it would if I were to just copy and paste my code several different times, but the final code is much more readable and less prone to errors. By the time I’m done working, I have some interactive plots showing the significant and non-significant results. When you hover over them, they show what protein corresponds to which point on the graph. They look like this, except this is not the real data we used in her study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/volcano.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Rstudio and its amazing Rmarkdown tool to craft a draft report to the researcher, and I save it with today’s date in my “Reports” folder for that project. The report so far includes unadjusted and adjusted models of all the protein expressions using very small p-values to account for the 1000+ statistical comparisons we’re making. I show the results in various plots such as the one above (called a “volcano plot” for its shape).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also started writing code for models to determine which proteins are most different, or uniquely expressed, between subgroups of patients. Tomorrow, I will use a technique common in machine learning, called clustering, to see if these protein expressions can correctly classify subgroups of patients. The goal is to find a minimum group of proteins to identify patients of interest who have both the autoimmune disorder and the lung disease my collaborator is interested in. One way this research could be impactful is that it may help determine which proteins pharmaceuticals should develop drugs to target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I close the report; I will continue working on this analysis tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4:45PM - It’s time for my last meeting of the day. I head to another floor of my office building and get my laptop set up in a conference room. I await the arrival of several doctors. It will be my first time meeting most of them, and our task today is to discuss the data collection process for a future study involving both genetic mutation data from tumor biopsies and clinical data from electronic health records on thousands of patients with lung cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5:00PM - The doctors arrive and, after introductions, we talk about the current stage of the project and what the goals are. We discuss the timing of starting chart reviews of patients, how we will upload the information to a database efficiently, and what might be the best way to condense the highly detailed genetics data into useful information for an analysis. Our solution will likely involve a series of iterative searches through the columns containing genetic information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/redcap.png&#34; alt=&#34;ma&#34;width=&#34;600px&#34; height=&#34;425px&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6:00PM - The meeting ends, and I go back to my desk to record more handwritten notes. I log the hours I spent on each project that day into Toggl, which is the time-tracking application our team uses. This is so we know how much time we’re spending on each project, and is as much for our own sake as it is anyone else’s. I update my to-do list, which is a giant color-coded excel spreadsheet, and eat a few chocolate covered raisins as my reward for a productive day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6:30PM - I leave work! I typically have some kind of activity, like happy hour (see my cute cubicle buddies below), a sports game, or Spanish class that I’m heading off to. Some days I attend coding workshops hosted by groups such as R-ladies. On nights when I’m feeling especially nerdy, I’ll go home and read a statistics paper or sift through the #rstats tips on twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/coworkers.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34; height=&#34;375px&#34; alt=&#34;cowies&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…So, there you have it. One average daily experience as an early career masters-level statistician. All in all, I have a fantastic work-life balance and overall work environment. Every day I get to learn more about science, medicine, statistics, and the intersection of these wonderful ideas. Although it varies quite a bit, approximately 10% of each day involves writing, 20% interacting with other researchers, and the rest of it is spent thinking critically and finding answers to problems I am passionate about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope if there are any 22, 42, or 14 year-olds out there considering a career in biostatistics and struggling to figure out what on earth we actually do, that you find this post and it lessens your confusion! Feel free to reach out to me if you have questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Not a real statistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Exact details and diseases of the studies I am currently working on have been generalized or altered to protect the research interests of my collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Day in the Life of a Biostatistician</title>
      <link>/blog/testing/ditl-biostats/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/blog/testing/ditl-biostats/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;It seems fitting that my first blog post is on a topic that I tried and failed to find via Google search a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll back up for a second. A few years ago I was a recent college graduate, and trying hard to “figure out my life.” My major was biochemistry, which is one of those degrees where 99%* of people just keep on going to school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was working full-time night-shift at a hospital as a patient care technician. The key word in that sentence is “night-shift” which meant that even on my days off, I didn’t sleep at night, but all my friends and family did. So, I was often alone and awake, with a lot of time to think about my future… and surf the web for potential careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/sadcat.png&#34; width=&#34;340px&#34; height=&#34;450px&#34; alt=&#34;cat&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew I wanted a job in healthcare, but I was confused as to where in medicine would be a good fit for me. I could visualize very clearly what my days at work would look like if I were to become a physician, or a physician assistant, or a registered nurse (all careers I developed lengthy pros and cons lists for).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there was another career involving medicine that I was drawn to but didn’t know enough about. “Biostatistics” was a class biochemistry majors took at my university, but I had been exempted because I took AP Statistics in high school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, biostatistics seemed to be the application of some high school-level math to biological problems. I had no concept of what a degree in biostatistics, and much less a career as a biostatistician, could entail. Endless Google searches with some variant of “what does a biostatistician do” and even “day in the life of a biostatistician” had not given me a very good picture of what I would actually be doing as a biostatistician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ultimately lucked out during a conversation with a professor during my senior year of college. I was rambling about my many life plans and he mentioned his cousin was the chair of a well-known Biostatistics program. He encouraged me to email her my questions about biostatistics, and I am so grateful she took time to respond with detailed answers. Her description of life as a biostatistician was enough for me to choose going to graduate school for an MS in biostatistics over medical school/physician assistant school/second-degree nursing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel wholeheartedly that although I would have enjoyed my life as an MD/PA/RN, biostatistics is the right career for me. So, in honor of my confused younger self, and as a way of paying it forward, I’ve dedicated this topic for my very first blog post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/maz.png&#34; alt=&#34;ma&#34;width=&#34;400px&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full disclaimer - what follows is a day in the life of one masters-level, academic research-focused biostatistician and I cannot make claims about the careers of statisticians in industry or pharmaceuticals or hospitals or government. In addition, here’s a bit more background before I get into the granular details of my work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My official job description is to assist investigators (i.e. physicians or PhD-level researchers with a scientific question) throughout all stages of the scientific research process. This means helping with study design, data collection, data cleaning (also known as getting the data in the right form for analysis and making sure nothing is obviously incorrect), data visualization, statistical analysis, reporting and explaining my results, and writing methods and results sections for scientific papers. You will soon see that on any given day I am working on multiple projects at various stages of this process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will mention R/Rstudio a bit. For those who are not familiar with it, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source (which means anyone can help contribute) programming language that is well-equipped for statistical analysis. It’s arguably very similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.python.org/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, which is a more widely used language, but statisticians tend to use R more because its statistical packages are very well-developed. During grad school I used Python because I worked in a computational biology lab, and I learned &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sas.com/en_us/home.html&#34;&gt;SAS&lt;/a&gt; (another statistical programming language) in some of my classes, but R is what I prefer these days. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;Rstudio&lt;/a&gt; is a platform that makes it more user friendly to use R.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, without further ado! An average day**:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/desk.png&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34; height=&#34;375px&#34; alt=&#34;desky&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9:30AM - I arrive at my office and spend a few minutes chatting with my coworkers. To set the scene for you, I have a fairly spacious cubicle within a group of five other cubicles. I sit next to another research biostatistician, two health informatics professionals, and two clinical trial grant specialists. I’m actually not completely sure what that last pair’s title is, but I know their primary task is to make sure several multi-million dollar clinical trial grants stay funded (woah). Everyone I sit by is young and goofy, but very driven, making for a fun office environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9:45AM - I check and answer new emails from researchers I collaborate on projects with. I send my availability for a meeting to a group of doctors who want to go over the results of a recent analysis I did on Body Mass Index and death rates in the Intensive Care Unit. In a different thread of emails, I thank several researchers from another university for clarifying their methods and sending me code for an analysis similar to one I will soon work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:00AM - I open a manuscript draft for a paper I received yesterday. It’s from a group of residents and medical students I worked with a few months ago. Their study looks at the association between blood levels of a certain biomarker and the time to death in cancer patients. My role in the analysis was to examine the associations between several biomarkers such as phosphorus, phosphate, and calcitriol. I then fit a regression model, just like y=mx+b, but with way more math. For this analysis I used a model for when your y is a time to an event (death, in this case), fittingly called a survival model. After adjusting for confounding factors like age, which affects both tumor progression and biomarker levels, there was a significant association between the biomarker and time to death in cancer patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers have asked for my assistance in writing the methods section. The methods section of a scientific article is the steps the scientists took to analyze data explicitly written out for anyone looking to review or learn about their work. I read through their current draft of the paper carefully, make some edits, and send it back. They are hoping to submit this paper to a peer-reviewed journal within a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/KM.png&#34; width=&#34;650px&#34; height=&#34;500px&#34; alt=&#34;kmplot&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:45AM - I have a weekly meeting a few blocks from my office with a neurologist I spend a large portion of my time working with. She is a leader in the field of Alzheimer’s research, and I find it very rewarding to work on her data and be a small part of a growing body of research in the field. I am “contracted” out to her research as I am to all of the researchers I work with—it’s how my institution budgets funding for grants. One of the faculty-level biostatisticians in my department—which means he has a PhD and specializes in certain statistical methods—is also part of this contract, and some days, like today, he joins me at these meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11:00AM - This week’s meeting is pretty straightforward. We discuss how we can improve one of the neurologist’s National Institute of Health grants from a statistics standpoint. The statistical methods for this project can get complicated, in part because we are looking at the brain scans of women in different stages of menopause over time, and we have to consider age as a confounding factor. We want to convey to the reviewers of our grant how we plan to do this. Since this is a methods-focused meeting, I mostly listen and take notes along with two neurology research coordinators that also attend these weekly meetings. When the meeting concludes I have for less work than usual - I only need to make a few graphs representing our study design and past results for inclusion to the grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12:00PM - I head to lunch with a group of coworkers. They have gotten food from a nearby salad place, and we sit in one of our favorite buildings on campus and eat together. Our jokes oscillate from incredibly nerdy to pretty stupid. One of my coworkers points out that our hair is styled the same way for the third day in a row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/katalan.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12:45PM - I get back to my desk and type up my handwritten notes from the neurology meeting and put them in that project’s “Notes” folder. It’s important to me that I keep track of all my meetings electronically - I fear losing my notebooks or someone else having to decipher my cursive should I ever have to pass off a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1:00PM - I start to make a plan for a different analysis I’m working on. This project is something new for me - it involves a protein assay and data for 1000+ different protein expression levels. The researcher I’m working with wants to know which proteins are over- and under-expressed in people with a specific autoimmune disorder and a certain type of lung disease. I’ve recently spoken to some bioinformaticians and have a clearer idea of the analysis I need to do. I draw out a little map of the code organization I think would be the most efficient for this analysis and open up Rstudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/notes.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400px&#34; height=&#34;350px&#34; alt=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1:30PM - I get to work writing up functions, which is just a fancy programming way of saying your code can do the same thing to multiple data sets (or subsets of patients, as is the case of this protein expression study I’m doing). Sometimes it takes a bit longer to write my functions than it would if I were to just copy and paste my code several different times, but the final code is much more readable and less prone to errors. By the time I’m done working, I have some interactive plots showing the significant and non-significant results. When you hover over them, they show what protein corresponds to which point on the graph. They look like this, except this is not the real data we used in her study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/volcano.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Rstudio and its amazing Rmarkdown tool to craft a draft report to the researcher, and I save it with today’s date in my “Reports” folder for that project. The report so far includes unadjusted and adjusted models of all the protein expressions using very small p-values to account for the 1000+ statistical comparisons we’re making. I show the results in various plots such as the one above (called a “volcano plot” for its shape).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also started writing code for models to determine which proteins are most different, or uniquely expressed, between subgroups of patients. Tomorrow, I will use a technique common in machine learning, called clustering, to see if these protein expressions can correctly classify subgroups of patients. The goal is to find a minimum group of proteins to identify patients of interest who have both the autoimmune disorder and the lung disease my collaborator is interested in. One way this research could be impactful is that it may help determine which proteins pharmaceuticals should develop drugs to target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I close the report; I will continue working on this analysis tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4:45PM - It’s time for my last meeting of the day. I head to another floor of my office building and get my laptop set up in a conference room. I await the arrival of several doctors. It will be my first time meeting most of them, and our task today is to discuss the data collection process for a future study involving both genetic mutation data from tumor biopsies and clinical data from electronic health records on thousands of patients with lung cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5:00PM - The doctors arrive and, after introductions, we talk about the current stage of the project and what the goals are. We discuss the timing of starting chart reviews of patients, how we will upload the information to a database efficiently, and what might be the best way to condense the highly detailed genetics data into useful information for an analysis. Our solution will likely involve a series of iterative searches through the columns containing genetic information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/redcap.png&#34; alt=&#34;ma&#34;width=&#34;600px&#34; height=&#34;425px&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6:00PM - The meeting ends, and I go back to my desk to record more handwritten notes. I log the hours I spent on each project that day into Toggl, which is the time-tracking application our team uses. This is so we know how much time we’re spending on each project, and is as much for our own sake as it is anyone else’s. I update my to-do list, which is a giant color-coded excel spreadsheet, and eat a few chocolate covered raisins as my reward for a productive day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6:30PM - I leave work! I typically have some kind of activity, like happy hour (see my cute cubicle buddies below), a sports game, or Spanish class that I’m heading off to. Some days I attend coding workshops hosted by groups such as R-ladies. On nights when I’m feeling especially nerdy, I’ll go home and read a statistics paper or sift through the #rstats tips on twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/hoffmakl/khoffman_website/master/content/blog/coworkers.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34; height=&#34;375px&#34; alt=&#34;cowies&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…So, there you have it. One average daily experience as an early career masters-level statistician. All in all, I have a fantastic work-life balance and overall work environment. Every day I get to learn more about science, medicine, statistics, and the intersection of these wonderful ideas. Although it varies quite a bit, approximately 10% of each day involves writing, 20% interacting with other researchers, and the rest of it is spent thinking critically and finding answers to problems I am passionate about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope if there are any 22, 42, or 14 year-olds out there considering a career in biostatistics and struggling to figure out what on earth we actually do, that you find this post and it lessens your confusion! Feel free to reach out to me if you have questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Not a real statistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Exact details and diseases of the studies I am currently working on have been generalized or altered to protect the research interests of my collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
